A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    - 1799 August 26 Edmund Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses previous correspondence; the death of Wilson Cary Nicholas' brother, George Nicholas [on July 25, 1799] in Kentucky, and its effect upon his family; and debts due to Wilson Cary Nicholas, including: 1. money paid to Fairfax's executors, 2. a bond due to Meriwether Smith, 3. The assignment from the securities of Colonel G[eorge?] N[icholas?], and 4. Various other claims Randolph outlines his opinions on these debts and how they should be paid. He mentions that he will give Nicholas the notice by Saturday morning and will meet him at the Goochland Courthouse on Sunday, 5 pages (Box-folder 1:58)
    - 1799 September 11 Samuel Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a deal to alleviate a debt through another loan. Part of the loan needed is for £30000 that George Nicholas owed on his death. Original proposal is quoted from a letter from July 5 th, 1799, and these two pages of quoted material suggests that a loan of £9000 cannot be made but one of £6000 can be. The second part suggests that he cannot supply the loan until Nicholas gets his other business ventures together, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:59)
    - 1799 October 08 Wilson Cary Nicholas to General [Samuel] Smith, discusses the proposed loan from Smith to repay debts that George Nicholas left. Goes into detail about how he plans on paying the loan off. Thanks Smith for a promise of $6000, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:60)
    - [1799] November 12 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Samuel Smith, left Kentucky on the 10 th accompanied by his niece Maria due to her inappropriate attachment to Norborne Nelson, discusses the inheritance and property left by George Nicholas, especially that portion left to his wife Polly as her dower. Nicholas believes she ought not to relinquish her dower for any reason because one of his brother's debts, 2,115 pounds, was demanded immediately upon his death, but her dower could not be touched to satisfy this. Talks about the various property and potential value of George's holdings, including his slaves, interest in the Barbour Iron Works, and his land upon Eagle Creek, including a valuable salt lick; how debts will be paid off, and where money for his survivors will come from. Brings up John G. Owings, a partner in the iron works, and whether or not he will be able to buy out George Nicholas' share, 5 pages (Box-folder 1:61)
    - 1800 January 11 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Mr. [George?] Wythe's reactions to and opinions concerning Nicholas' list of ten exceptions the lawsuit of Macon v Ambler, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:62)
    - 1800 January 16 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [G. Fisher], discusses Nicholas's frustration with the prolonged issues and the continuing developments in regard to the execution of George Nicholas's debts and the acquisition of a loan, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:63)
    - 1800 January 20 Joseph H. Davies to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the payment of interest and debts. Provides news from home and congratulates Nicholas on his election to Congress, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:64)
    - 1800 February 06 Wilson Cary Nicholas to [?], Draft concerning debts in relation to George Nicholas and the payment of those debts. He has already paid £4000 in Virginia money and has $10,000 in the bank. The letter is incomplete, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:65)
    - 1800 March 21 John Reed to Morrison and Davies, accepts Wilson Cary Nicholas's plan to pay him for the debt that George Nicholas left upon his death, 1 page (Box-folder 1:66)
    - 1800 March 26 James Morrison to Samuel Smith, discusses Reed to whom Nicholas and Smith owe $1000 and interest. Also, they have two other bonds out—one for £ 115 and the other for £2000, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:67)
    - 1800 March 29 Joseph H Davies to Wilson Cary Nicholas, contains a proposal of the payment for George Nicholas's debts. Wilson Nicholas will pay $1,000 within five years and will also pay yearly interest, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:68)
    - 1800 March 30 James Morrison to General Samuel Smith, encourages Smith and Wilson Nicholas to take immediate action on Reed's proposal for the debt settlement, 1 page (Box-folder 1:69)
    - 1800 April 05 William Green to General Samuel Smith, Green writes to say he will draw up the contract between Reed, Smith, and Wilson Nicholas upon receiving bonds from Nicholas and Smith, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:70)
    - 1800 May 20 Joseph H. Davies to Wilson Cary Nicholas, continues the discussion of the loan and agreement to settle George Nicholas's debt to Reed. This letter agrees to the proposals but needs to be finalized by all parties, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:71)
    - 1800 July 10 [J. Morrison?] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the transfer of funds in the bank, 1 page (Box-folder 1:72)
    - 1800 August 04 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas and General Samuel Smith, Samuel Smith to James Morrison on the bottom (1800 August 29) Morrison writes to say that he has withdrawn the money to pay the debt. Smith acknowledges this letter, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:73)
    - 1800 August 07 Samuel Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the legislative branches and their likely motives in voting and how that will affect the government: "they will call together to present legislature to measure the laws. The Senate a dead force will carry against the republican votes in the House—he is wrong, I believe, in his conjecture there's one Election annually, they will not freely resigne their own Situation to forward that of the president,", 3 pages (Box-folder 1:74)
    - 1800 August James Monroe to Wilson Cary Nicholas, printed letter explaining that one thousand arms have been sent to the 47 th regiment, 1 page (Box-folder 1:75)
    - 1800 October 12 Samuel Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses repaying bills and debts which are not binding without the words "value receiverae." Also discusses the establishment of local elected officials, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:76)
    - 1801 January 19 Colonel T. Blackbourne to Levin Powell, discusses a present dilemma in the choice of a president between Jefferson and Burr who are tied but whose election will be decided in February by the House of Representatives. Warns of danger of civil war and disagrees with both Jefferson and Burr's views and politics. Jefferson, Blackbourne believes, has best abilities, but "he may by his fine spun theories break the thread of our government and make us a poor—divided—contemptible and dependent people." Jefferson's commercial view would commit the trade of our country to foreign nations. "Pray what has been done in Mr. Nicholas' Resolutions for a regular system of choosing [the] president and Vice President? Are there any, and what objections to it? [Levin Powell (1737-1810) was the US Representative of Virginia; Blackbourne (1740-1807 was a revolutionary war patriot.], 4 pages (Box-folder 1:77)
    - 1801 April 06 James Monroe to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], Monroe apologizes for replying so late and then says that he hopes that he will be able to provide the requested money but is not sure where he would be able to find the funds to do so, transferred to Vault, James Monroe papers, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:78)
    - 1801 September 11 R. Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], indicates that the first bill for $3000 became due on September 11 and that he has taken an extension on it for a period of 60 days, so Nicholas need not worry about it. Also informs Nicholas of the death of Smith's son, Robert, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:79)
    - 1801 September 29 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, expresses Morrison's displeasure and anger in Nicholas who apparently asked questions about Morrison's character while in Washington. Morrison launches into an extended defense of himself and his previous actions, 7 pages (Box-folder 1:80)
    - 1801 December 28 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Morrison's intention to travel to Washington to meet with the Secretary of Treasury, to ascertain whether he could be paid for previous financial service to the country, to clear his name, and to improve his health. He continues to express his pleasure in the change to a popular administration and how this new administration will be much better for the country. He concludes by providing Nicholas with news about his family, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:81)
    - 1802 January 25 James Madison to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], Fragment, torn half page, Seems to discuss a bank, transferred to Vault, James Madison papers (Box-folder 1:82)
    - 1802 February 15 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas and Samuel Smith, discusses the issues continuing to surround the estate of George Nicholas's and his debts. Speaks at some length about the need to prolong the processing of these debts, (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box), 4 pages (Box-folder 1:83)
    - 1802 February 16 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses George Nicholas's family who lives in Kentucky, urging Wilson Nicholas to move to that state in order to care for and to provide for his sister-in-law and his brother's children. Mentions his application to Congress for compensation for extra duty. Also encourages Wilson Nicholas to speak with General Smith about his contract with Mr. Williamson. (Box-folder 1:84)
    - 1802 July 20 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the duty owed to Williamson of £2000 and the need to act on the deal within the next three months, preferably within the next four to six months so that more debt is not accrued and so that George Nicholas's children can be self-sufficient, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:85)
    - 1803 February 06 Bishop James Madison to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], acknowledges the receipt of $100 for Robert, a student at William and Mary and [son of Nicholas?]. Discusses the conduct and possible placement of Robert with the new tutor for modern languages, geography, and civil history, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:86)
    - 1803 March 10 S[amuel] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], answer from Wilson Cary Nicholas on bottom. Smith acknowledges Nicholas's request for $5438.26 to Davidson Williamson, 1 page (Box-folder 1:87)
    - 1803 March 28 R[ober]t Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses some political issues especially those relating to the 'western country,' including the type of Federalism there. Also questions Nicholas on the state of Pennsylvania. Speculates on the longevity of certain political careers, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:88)
    - 1803 April 10 John Taylor of Caroline to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses judgments made concerning a debt. Also indicates that after this present business, Taylor will no longer engage in financial trade and negotiation with Nicholas, 1 page (Box-folder 1:89)
    - 1803 June 10 Peyton Randolph to [W. C. Nicholas?], declines an offer to collect money in Goochland county because Randolph does not live there. Instead suggests that Charles Bates would be a better candidate and informs Nicholas that he has already instructed Bates in how to proceed, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:90)
    - 1803 October 02 L.H. Lean to S[amuel] Smith, discusses the treatment of a young woman who seems to have not been improving despite a series of medicine and a regimen to help her. Lean suggests that Smith should consult other sources including Colonel Nicholas and that he should pay Nicholas $100, 1 page (Box-folder 1:91)
    - 1804 March 15 M.B.N. [Mary B. Nicholas] to 'Pappa' [Wilson Cary Nicholas], expresses her inability to commit to a union with 'Mr. H[arvie?]' for whom she does not have the affection 'that would render a union with him either happy or honourable.' Also expresses concern that she has let her father down and that it might appear she has misled Mr. [L. Harvie?], 1 page (Box-folder 1:92)
    - [1804 March] Wilson Cary Nicholas to L. H[arvie?], draft. Wilson's daughter Mary wrote her father on March 14 about how to break off an engagement to a Mr. H[arvie]. This letter is a draft that Wilson composed for her to give Mr. H. with an explanation of why she must break off the engagement, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:93)
    - 1804 April 14 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, predicts a very close upcoming election concerning [Aaron?] Burr and the possible consequences if he is elected or not, 1 page (Box-folder 1:94)
    - 1804 July 21 S[amuel] Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], refers to his concern over the new post of Collector at Norfolk taken by Nicholas, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:95)
    - 1804 August 22 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, with a Bill of Account enclosed, discusses an account with Mr. Rutherford and how the money involved in that account has thus far been dealt with. Also suggests that Nicholas's balance has been reviewed and balanced, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:96)
    - 1804 November 10 D. Carr to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], makes a second request for money that Nicholas owes Carr so that Carr can make necessary payments, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:97)
    - 1805 January 29 Wilson Cary Nicholas to General [Abram] Trigg, discusses an offer that Trigg made for some land of Nicholas's. Nicholas is upset at the smallness of the offer and makes a detailed counter- offer, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:98)
    - 1805 March 28 & 30 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Peggy [his wife, Margaret Smith], tries to reassure her about the unfavorable comments people have made about him and his decision to leave the Senate and take the post of Collector at Norfolk which was based upon the advice of both her brothers and the President [Jefferson] and discussion with herself, 8 pages (Box-folder 1:99)
    - 1805 April 20 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his thankfulness that the [ship Canton] is reported safe, as it had considerable cargo; discusses the Enquirer, [William Duane?], and the tyranny of the press as exhibited by the Philadelphia newspaper Aurora, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:100)
    - 1805 April 29 Albert Gallatin to Wilson Cary Nicholas, marked private. Relays Gallatin's regret that 'any circumstance should render Hay's interference unpleasant either to him or to you: but the district attorney is the officer uniformly and necessarily employed in cases of this kind. My own impression is that, on further investigation, you will find the responsibility you so generously wish to assume greater both in extent and risk than you had supposed." (Box-folder 1:101)
    - 1805 November 25 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the final decree obtained in his name against the heirs and executors of George Nicholas, whose effects will be sold by the commissioners in seven weeks. Morrison also indicates that he will be heading to Washington in the next days with Nicholas's niece and will bring her to Baltimore by Christmas time, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:102)
    - 1805 December 27 David Bullock to Wilson Cary Nicholas. Enclosed is a bill of sale for slaves, discusses the procedures and value of slaves purchased by Nicholas that are to be delivered to Goochland County. Also enclosed are the lists of named slaves, their price, and the destination of each one by group to "Carrs Bridge," "Sans Souci," and "Goochland,", 4 pages (Box-folder 1:103)
    - 1806 January 12 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, assures that there is every reason for a suit against the Carters, 1 page (Box-folder 1:104)
    - 1806 January 22 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that one of Nicholas's debtors, Mr. Owings, cannot pay him back because he is not as independent of his father as they thought. Suggests that George Nicholas's farm should be titled in two names to combat future creditor problems. Urges Nicholas to get Randolph or Robert Smith to help because they have a great deal of influence. Asks Nicholas to write to Nancy Nicholas because of her present difficult situation amongst strangers, 6 pages (Box-folder 1:105)
    - 1806 February 04 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, relays what took place in an interview with S[amuel?] Smith, who agreed to take land from Owings instead of money for past debts. Advises that Wilson Cary Nicholas should give some land and money to Mrs. [George] Nicholas upon receipt of the money that Owings owes. Repeats that in present situation, land is much more valuable than money in the repayment of debts, 8 pages (Box-folder 1:106)
    - [1806] March 11 [Samuel Smith] to [ ? ], fragment, discusses the Miranda Case which concerns Francisco de Miranda who fought for Venezuelan independence in 1806 but was defeated. The letter indicates that Miranda had met with both [James] Madison and President [Jefferson] in the hopes of gaining support for his rebellion. After he was defeated and his ship, The Leander, was taken captive, several US citizens—notably Samuel Ogden and William Smith—were tried. Considers issues of acceptable governmental decision making in the realm of international affairs, 1 page (Box-folder 1:107)
    - 1806 March 19 John Taylor to Wilson Cary Nicholas, describes the loss of two of Taylor's sons. Contains a discussion of the coming presidential election between James Madison and James Monroe with the opinion that there are numerous plots and rumors surrounding Madison. Reflects on how age has tempered his opinions, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:108)
    - 1806 March 21 S[amuel] Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, note: "Burn this letter." Mentions the burial of General [James] Jackson (1757- 1806) on March 20, 1806 with every possible honor and believes he will be missed greatly in the [Senate?]. Believes the Senate grows weaker at every change and says that Mr. [Thomas?] Worthington has taken the head and quotes boldly what the President wants. The President must attend to public opinion. Smith was told that [John] Armstrong (1758-1843), minister to France, had completely lost the confidence of his friends, and that to buoy him up, [President Jefferson] joined [James] Bowdoin to Armstrong to help make the final arrangements with Spain. The Vice President [George Clinton] told [Jefferson] that there was such hostility to Armstrong that any treaty made by him would be in danger. Smith states, "The business is to bribe France with seven millions of dollars to counsel [miserable?] Spain to give us the Floridas & fix our western boundary. The vote of Senate, the recommendations & Entreaty of Friends, desiring a Mission might be sent to London had no effect on the President- he was absolutely was determined not to do it." Smith also refers to the "loud language of John Randolph" [of Roanoke?], the need to replace [James] Monroe "(who is notorious)" in Great Britain with a Federalist, who is a well-informed merchant, and comments about Randolph, "I am far from approving the conduct of Mr. R. It was highly indiscreet & improper - had done a great deal of mischief - nor is he done - It will do more - It will shake the confidence of the people in the President." He also refers to the Speaker [Joseph Hopper?] Nicholson's disgust and determination to leave public life, the Spanish pressing on the United States western border and a recent fight to drive them across the Sabine River., 3 pages (Box-folder 1:109)
    - 1806 March 27 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that he had waited for an answer about printing George Nicholas's Law Notes but never heard from W. Nicholas or his brother. Morrison is now giving up on the project because he presumes that Randolph and the brother of Nicholas thought it is improper to continue. Goes on to say that Mr. Owings, Sr. is unwilling to give up land to pay his son's debts, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:110)
    - 1806 April 03 [Wilson Cary Nicholas] to S[amuel] Smith, acknowledges a letter from the President discussing the possibility of including him in the mission to France with Armstrong and Bowdoin over the claim to the Floridas, "I was never more embarrassed in my life. I feel with great force the obligation that every man is under to serve his country. My attachment to the President is such, that nothing could be more painful to me, than to refuse to comply with his wishes." Neither does he feel such a mission to be improper since our contract [for the Louisiana Purchase] was with France and France is honor bound to help resolve any border disputes with Spain. Indicates his distrust and apprehension concerning Great Britain, including impressments and the seizure of American vessels, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:111)
    - 1806 April 07 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, believes that John Randolph's attacks upon the President has caused some to rally around him and to vote for Armstrong and that the report of [Stephen Row?] Bradley displeased the President & Madison without cause as the peace with Tripoli [ending the war against the Barbary pirates] was shameful and the Committee wished to fix the blame where it was due, upon [Tobias] Lear. They also disapprove of the conduct of Commodore Barron in the war. Rumor says that John Adams will also have a foreign mission to Constantinople. Finally writes "burn this letter,", 3 pages (Box-folder 1:112)
    - 1806 April 08 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that he has met with the older Mr. Owings who says he might be willing to discharge his son's debts with land, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:113)
    - 1806 April 20 James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, apologizes for his last letter which accused Nicholas of not caring about his brother, George Nicholas, his legacy, and his family. Expresses his continued love and admiration for Wilson Nicholas, 6 pages (Box-folder 1:114)
    - 1806 May 16 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, after opening his letter with the adage: "there are such things as the lie outright, the fib, and the white lie," Smith accuses [Jefferson] of deceit, if he claimed that Smith had been considered as a third person on the Spanish mission. Instead, Smith believed that "the place I ought to have been named for was a third with Monroe and Pinckney to make the Commercial Treaty at Great Britain. Neither of them can know anything of the practical concerns of this country - everybody expected such an offer to me." Continues to express his frustration at his exclusion from the mission to Great Britain and mentions Stephen Higginson, "the head of the Essex Junto one of the best informed merchants in the Union,", 3 pages (Box-folder 2:1)
    - 1806 May 23 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, states that Mr. Pinckney sailed with his family on Wednesday and was visited before his departure by all the Federalist gentleman, but not by a single Republican. According to Smith, "Mr. J[efferson], told Senators who had to vote [on Pinckney's confirmation,] "that Mr. Pinckney was as good a Republican as any other man of our family", 2 pages (Box-folder 2:2)
    - 1806 July 13 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, after learning of Mrs. George Nicholas's death, Smith writes in regard to how the land and finances should be divided and titled. Suggests Nelson go to sea. Also says that he knows that some money--$600 to 800— has been left to Margaretta, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 1806 July 21 S[amuel] S[mith] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the current circumstances surrounding George Nicholas's orphaned family. Indicates that leaving young children—especially girls— without protection is dangerous and suggests that they attempt to have the Morrison's take in Margaretta and George, as Nancy will likely be married soon and Nelson can go into the navy, or to him; Smith offers to take Samuel; and believes Georgeanna, Elizabeth Randolph, and [Hetty] Morrison will be taken by Mrs. Morrison, 2 pages (Box-folder 2:4)